<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Briefe discourse declaring and approving the necessary and inviolable maintenance of the laudable customes of London namely, of that one, whereby a reasonable partition of the goods of husbands among their wives and children is provided : with an answer to such objections and pretenced reasons, as are by persons unadvised or evill perswaded, used against the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08092268</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08092268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1224:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Briefe discourse declaring and approving the necessary and inviolable maintenance of the laudable customes of London namely, of that one, whereby a reasonable partition of the goods of husbands among their wives and children is provided : with an answer to such objections and pretenced reasons, as are by persons unadvised or evill perswaded, used against the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>p. 45-75.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Flesher, Printer to that Honourable City,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ordinances, Municipal --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>Customary law --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40820:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DISCOURSE, DECLARING And approving the neceſſary and inviolable maintenance of THE LAUDABLE CUSTOMES OF <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Namely, of that one, whereby a reaſonable partition of the goods of husbands among their Wives and Children is provided:</p>
            <p>With an anſwer to ſuch objections and pretenced reaſons, as are by perſons unadviſed or evill perſwaded, uſed againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by JAMES FLESHER, Printer to that Honourable City, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:40820:2"/>
            <head>Juris civilis de conſuetudine Axiomata ſive Maximae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Conſuetudo vim habet rei Judicatae.</item>
               <item>Conſuetudo eſt optima legum interpres.</item>
               <item>Conventio &amp; conſuetudo vincunt legem.</item>
               <item>Conſuetudo firmata eſt ubi ſimili aliquando contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto, Iudicio quid eſt obtentum ſeu Iudicatum.</item>
               <item>Coepta uſucapio vel praeſcriptio per defunctum, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuatur per haeredem, cum in omne jus defuncti ſuccedat haeres.</item>
               <item>Profunda requie humano generi proſpexit uſucapio. Barto.</item>
               <item>Uſucapio eſt quies periculi ſolicitudiniſque litium. Cicero.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40820:2"/>
            <head>A Briefe Diſcourſe, declaring and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the neceſſary and inviolable main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the laudable Cuſtomes of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E finde it neceſſary in all common-wealths, for ſubjects to live under the direction of Lawes, conſtitutions or cuſtomes publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known and received, and not to depend onely upon the commandement and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the governour, bee the ſame never ſo juſt or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in life and converſation. For that the Law once enacted and eſtabliſhed, extendeth his execution to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men alike without favour or affection: whereas if the word of a Prince were a Law, the ſame being a mortall man, muſt needs be poſſeſſed with thoſe paſſions, and inclinations of favour or disfavour that other men be: and ſometimes decline from the conſtant and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable levell of indifferency, to reſpect the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the matter, if not to regard the perſon more then the cauſe. Wherefore it was well agreed by the wiſeſt Philoſophers and greateſt Politicks, that a dumb Lawes direction is to be preferred before the ſole diſpoſition of any living Prince, both for the cauſe afore touched, and for other reaſons which I will here omit. But to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the particularities of my intention, and to treat of the validitie and inviolable obſervation of ſome lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (I might term them ſacred) cuſtomes, being the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall joynts, and very ſinews of all good Corporations and Fellowſhips, and being alſo the maintainers of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40820:3"/>unity and naturall amity between the husband and his wife, the parents and their children, which (as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> the wiſe Philoſopher termeth it) is the beginning of a City. For what is a City but a manifold and joynt ſociety conſiſting of many houſholds, and living under the ſame Lawes, Freedomes and Franchiſes? ſo I muſt needs confeſs them to be the procurers and cauſes of ſundry good effects to the generall eſtate of the City wherein they be obſerved: as of the other ſide they may breed ſundry inconveniences in ſuch a City where the ſame are violated and broken with allowance and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I will therefore ſhortly ſhew the nature of a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and the difference which it holdeth from a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Law. And next I will declare how neceſſary the ſame are to manage the government, and to entertain the proſperity and traffique of this City: and namely that one good cuſtome which I intend to ſpeak of. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I will endevour to anſwer thoſe pretenſed reaſons, and colourable objections made againſt the preciſe mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and defence thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I ſuppoſe that a cuſtome which juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth that name, is of no leſs reverent regard and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then a written Law, paſſed and allowed in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which notwithſtanding I do grant that there are certain differences between a Law and a cuſtome: for the cuſtome taketh his force by degrees of time, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a certain people, or the better part thereof, but a Law ſpringeth up in an inſtant, and receiveth life from him that is of ſoveraign authority to command. A cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome enlargeth it ſelfe by plauſible entertainment, and acceptable circumſtances of time and occaſion, with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall liking and allowance, whereas a Law is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40820:3"/>and publiſhed by power and received by duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſtraint, and that often againſt the good will of them that are bound by it, for which cauſe <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> not improperly compared the Cuſtome to a King, and the Law to a Tyrant. Moreover the cuſtome doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promiſe a reward for obſervation, nor inflict a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for violation thereof: whereas the Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes importeth either a conſideration of gain, or a terrour of puniſhment or damage, if the ſame be not a Law of enlargement or permiſſion that diſanulleth the prohibitions of a former Law. Finally a cuſtome is applyed to the commodity of ſome one province, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit or City, and grounded upon a ſpeciall reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie or commodity,<note place="margin">See 34 <hi>H.</hi> 8. B. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, 59. A man may not preſcribe or plead a cuſtome <hi>per totam Angliam,</hi> for that is common Law and no cuſtom otherwiſe if the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome had been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be in ſuch a City or County, as <hi>Gavelkind Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> Fee and ſuch like. <hi>Borough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engliſh.</hi>
               </note> for thoſe perſons or place where it is obſerved: whereas the Law hath a generall reaſon, extended to the whole Nation bound by the ſame, without private conſideration of the due impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of any peculiar place or people. Therefore it is well ſaid, and put in ure by the common Lawyer, <hi>Quod conſuetudo ex rationabili cauſa profecta privat communem le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem,</hi> That a cuſtome grounded upon reaſonable and honeſt conſideration abridgeth or altereth the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the common Law. So that in cuſtomes the eſtate or condition of the people are to be reſpected, and ſuch cuſtomes as are conſonant to reaſon, and moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to the eſtate and quality of ſuch people, are to be allowed. For example; the cuſtome of <hi>Boroughengliſh,</hi> yet in force in ſundry places of <hi>England,</hi> whereby the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſonne is to inherite his fathers land, hath taken ſtrength by this reaſon, that the father may (if he be not careleſs and ſecure to do his children good) train up his elder Sons in ſome good Trade or Occupation by which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40820:4"/>they may be able to get their own living: whereas the youngeſt, by the impotency and tenderneſs of his yeers, may be perchance unapt and unable for ſuch inſtruction. And ſo the Cuſtome commendable that provideth for the reliefe of the young and impotent. Alſo by an old cuſtome of this Land, in ſundry Boroughs and Towns, Lands were deviſable by Will, though the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> pronounced ſuch deviſes to be void;<note place="margin">But ſee now the Stature of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 2. and 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 5. of Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> and the reaſon was, for that inhabitants of Boroughs or Cities, whoſe traffique and Trade reſteth much upon mutuall truſt and credite, are oftentimes indebted at the time of their death. Wherefore it was thought meet, that they might deviſe their land for the due ſatisfaction of their creditours, which to do, they were enabled by the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. In <hi>Kent</hi> and other places of this land, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of <hi>Gavelkinde</hi> is maintained, which importeth an equall diviſion of the inheritance to be made among all the brethren: a cuſtome partly grounded upon a naturall conſideration, for that all the Sonnes hold the like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of nature and deſert with their Parents, in the which they have an equall intereſt: and alſo ſuffered to take place in <hi>Kent,</hi> and other places of this Land, in thoſe dayes moſt inclinable to rebellion, to the intent to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeble their forces, and to bring their great houſes and families to impuiſſance and decay, thereby to diſable and diſcourage them from ſuch unlawfull and violent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</p>
            <p>And to come neerer to the matter, this famous and renowned City of <hi>London</hi> hath many laudable and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtomes: which though they derogate and differ much from the rules of the common Law, yet have they been not onely approved by inviolate experience of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40820:4"/>ages, but alſo have been of old ratified and confirmed by ſundry Acts of Parliament, &amp; Charters of Princes, and namely by the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magna Charte. ca. 9.</note> by theſe words following, <hi>Quod civitas</hi> London <hi>habeat omnes libertates ſuas antiquas &amp; conſuetudines quas habere conſuevit,</hi> which is, <hi>That the City of</hi> London <hi>have all their ancient liberties and cuſtomes which they have uſed to have.</hi> The words following for other Cities, &amp;c. be, <hi>Quod habeant omnes libertates &amp; liberas conſuetudines ſuas,</hi> which ſignifieth, <hi>that they ſhall ſtill retaine their liberties and free cuſtomes,</hi> that is to ſay, their freedomes and immunities, as to bee diſcharged of toll, pontage, and ſuch like: Whereas the City of <hi>London</hi> hath proviſion made by that eſtatute, for all uſages and cuſtomes whatſoever. Verily as the City of <hi>London</hi> beareth oddes, and prerogative over other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Engl.</hi> being the <hi>Metropolis</hi> or mother City there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo are the inhabitants of it no leſs neceſſary then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable members of the Commonwealth, in tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our commodities into other lands, and enriching us with the benefits and fruits of other countries. The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Citizens of the ſame had that preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as in other things, ſo alſo in their executions for cauſes capitall, that they ſhould not be crucified, being a death of great torment and infamy, but onely beheaded. The benefit of which cuſtome Saint <hi>Paul</hi> claimed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the time of <hi>Nero:</hi> pretending that hee was a Citizen of <hi>Rome.</hi> The ſaid Citizens alſo by the dignity and reputation of their City were not for any tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or offence to be fettered, whipped, or ſcourged, which priviledge likewiſe the ſaid Saint <hi>Paul</hi> took hold of, who being oppreſſed by the calumnious accuſations and outcries of the Jewes, was by commandement of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40820:5"/>
               <hi>Claudius Lyſias</hi> the Captain to be examined by torture of whips,<note place="margin">Acts. 22.</note> what was the cauſe of that generall murmure and exclamation of the people againſt him: yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by alleaging that hee was a free man of <hi>Rome,</hi> not onely delivered himſelfe from the injury and rage of the people, but alſo made the Captain much afraid of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or puniſhment for the indignity offered unto him, ſo great was the Majeſty of that City, and ſo reverent the reputation of all ſuch as were accounted members thereof. <hi>Athenaeus</hi> termed <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe dayes very fitly, <hi>Epitome totius orbis,</hi> an abridgement of the whole world, for the continuall concourſe and reſort of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thither. We may derive thence an argument for our purpoſe, that <hi>London</hi> being worthy that title, <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome totius Angliae,</hi> in reſpect of the neceſſary repair and frequent aſſembly of all eſtates therein, whether it be for Juſtice by the Lawes of this Land, which are here admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, or by trade of marchandiſe, which is here ſo great that it may bee termed <hi>totius occidentis emporium:</hi> and chiefly becauſe of the favourable and often ſojorn of our moſt royall and gracious Soveraign, whoſe Majeſties chamber this is as it alwayes hath been of her moſt noble progenitors: the ſame is no leſs worthy of ſundry prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences which by Cuſtome and Charter it enjoyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other Cities of this Land.</p>
            <p>We finde in our Law Books, that the Scholers of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> claimed a priviledge by cuſtome,<note place="margin">43 E. 3. fo. 17. Vide <hi>Brook,</hi> Preſer. 8.</note> to have prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any houſe or lodging, that was to be let in the City of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the ſame was allowed in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where Juſtice <hi>Finchden</hi> a man of great reckoning at that time ſaid, that it is reaſon that they which are principall Inſtruments of great good in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40820:5"/>the Commonwealth, ſhould have beneficiall cuſtomes for the maintenance of their ſocieties: the like reaſon (ſaith he) ſerveth for the Merchants of the ſtaple in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and alſo for the Juſtices of Aſſiſes, or Juſtices in Eyre, to have the like prerogative. Alſo it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to remember, that the Barons of the Land have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers prerogatives above other ſubjects, that is, they ſhall not be ſworn when they paſs upon their Peers, and if they bring an appeal, the defendant ſhall not wage battaile againſt them, and they are exempted out of all returnes in Juries, and ſhall not be ſworn in Leets, and all in reſpect of their dignity, and for the neceſſary uſe of them in government of the Commonwealth. So that perſons of needfull employment in the eſtate, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been favoured in all their honeſt cuſtomes or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, and eſpecially the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and the rather for the great preſumption and opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of their experience, who being trained by hard education, in great uſe of ſervice and affairs: and alſo by their travaile and traffique beyond the Seas, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall negotiation with other Nations muſt needs (by all reaſonable likelihood) procure unto themſelves great judgement and ſufficiency, to manage a politick Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their City, according unto that verſe of the Poet <hi>Homer</hi> in the beginning of his Treatiſe of wiſe <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> his adventures remembring his travaile into ſundry Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Cities.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dic mihi Muſa virum captae poſt temporae Troiae,</l>
               <l>Qui mores hominum multorum vidit &amp; urbes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſenſe whereof may be well expreſſed in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh verſe without rime thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>All travailers do gladly report great praiſe of Ulyſſes:</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40820:6"/>
               <l>For that he knew many mens manners, and ſaw many Cities.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which opinion of their policy and experience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and approved by the noble Princes of this Land in all ages doth evidently appear by the manner of their government, whereat ſtrangers do no leſs envy then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire ſeeing ſo populous a City, containing by true eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation more then 500 thouſands of all ſorts of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, managed not by cruell Viceroyes, as is <hi>Naples</hi> or <hi>Millain,</hi> neither by proud <hi>Podeſtà,</hi> as be moſt Cities in <hi>Italy,</hi> or inſolent Lieutenants or Preſidents, as are ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Cities in <hi>France,</hi> (whoſe Preſidents are noble men or Captaines, having their perſons environed with a guard of Souldiers, and holding their Cities poſſeſſed with a Garriſon, as well in the quieteſt calm of peace, as in the hotteſt combuſtion of war:) but by a man of Trade or a meer Merchant, who notwithſtanding, during the time of his Magiſtracy, carrieth himſelfe with that honourable magnificence in his port, and enſignes of eſtate, that the Conſuls, Tribunes or Pretors of <hi>Rome,</hi> (namely, when as the ſame was reduced to a Monarchy) much leſs the <hi>Podeſtà</hi> of any City in <hi>Italy,</hi> never bare the like repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of dignity, and that not onely in peaceable ſeaſons but in time of greateſt warre: for ſuch credit the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Land have ſtill repoſed in their fidelity and wiſe direction, that we have few examples in any Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of any noble man or other appointed to aſſiſt the Lord Mayor in his government, much leſs to be ſole Ruler or Lieutenant for the time, were the ſtate never ſo troubleſome, and the affaires of never ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and importance.</p>
            <p>And to adde a little more in proofe of the ſingular
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40820:6"/>good conceipt had of their ſervice to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that the ſame hath in all ages from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt given them prerogative above other Cities of this Land,<note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.32.</note> we read in the vii. yeer of <hi>Henry</hi> the vi. that in <hi>nativo habendo</hi> brought by the Lord to recover his vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, it was adjudged a good return made by the Sheriffe of <hi>London,</hi> that ſuch was the Cuſtome of <hi>London,</hi> that a villain having remained there the ſpace of one whole yeer and a day, could not bee fetched or removed out thence. For ſo great is the prerogative of that place, that it giveth protection to the villain or bondman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Lord, while the ſaid bondman ſhall be reſiant there. Likewiſe it was taken for a good cuſtome in the City of <hi>London,</hi> that no attaint ſhould be maintained for a ſuppoſed falſe verdict given in that City.<note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.32. and the ſame caſe was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged in 2 <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note> In the which caſe the Sheriffe of <hi>London</hi> made return upon a writ of attaint ſued againſt a <hi>Londoner,</hi> that ſuch was and had been alwayes the cuſtome of the City, that no at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taint ſhould be allowed againſt any Commoner or other Citizen of the ſame, for which cauſe he might not <hi>ſalvis libertatibus</hi> without impeachment of their liberties, ſerve or execute the writ. Then was there a writ directed out of the Chancery to the Juſtices of the Kings Bench with expreſs commandement to allow to the Mayor, Sheriffes and Citizens all their liberties, immunities and cuſtomes, and further out of that writ was a <hi>Venire facias</hi> directed to the Mayor and Sheriffes, whereby was day given them to come and make declaration of their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, at which day the parties plaintiffe and defendant being preſent, the Mayor and Sheriffes had full allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their cuſtomes, the Sheriffes were holden excuſed for their return, and the parties writ was abated, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40820:7"/>himſelfe puniſhed by impriſonment for his vexation. I have here at large remembred this caſe, to the end it may appear both what credit and opinion of conſcience and truth, the Law aſcribed to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and alſo how carefull and vigilant the Mayor and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes have alwayes been to preſerve and uphold their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, although ſithence that onely cuſtome was for eſpeciall cauſes abrogated by the Statute of 11.<note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. c. 21.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 7. and an attaint given in <hi>London.</hi> Moreover, we finde it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in <hi>M.</hi> 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that whereas a Citizen of <hi>London</hi> brought an appeal of Robbery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> 2 <hi>E.</hi> 3. cor. pl. 157.</note> and the defendant would have tryed his innocency by battail, as he may in ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe againſt another man, <hi>Wilby</hi> then Juſtice anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, that he was not to have allowance of battaile in an appeal commenced by a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> for that by cuſtome of their City they were exempted from it. The like appeal was ſued <hi>P.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3. cor. pl. 125</note> 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. wherein the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant made offer of the ſame Triall. And although hee that ſued the appeal, would have joyned battaile without regard of this franchiſe, the Lord Mayor with the reſt of the Corporation ſued a writ out of the Chancery, recit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their cuſtome or franchiſe, and prayed allowance of it in diſturbance of the battaile. 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Coron.</hi> 125.</p>
            <p>If a free man or free woman of <hi>London</hi> be committed to <hi>Ludgate,</hi> they are to be excuſed from the ignominy of Irons, if they can finde ſureties to be true priſoners, and if the ſum be not above an hundred pounds. Upon the like reaſon is that cuſtome eſtabliſhed for the liberall and milde impriſonment of the Citizens in <hi>Ludgate,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they have indulgence and favour to go abroad into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place by <hi>Baſton</hi> as we term it, under the gard and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendency of their Keeper, with whom they muſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40820:7"/>return again to the Priſon at night: a cuſtome verily, though quarrelled with by ſome, and ſuppoſed to be the hinderance and delay of Juſtice, and oftentimes a mean to defraud men of their true debts and executions, yet the ground thereof being well examined, it wanteth not a ſound maintenance in the courſe of reaſon (as I think.) For the preſcription or cuſtome is but a mitigation of the extremity of their impriſonment, ſerving rather for the expedition of their diſcharge, and ſpeedy ſatisfaction of their creditours, then for any other purpoſe: ſo that this ſcope and licence in proper conſtruction and ſenſe of Law, cannot be termed an enlargement or liberty. For to remain in the materiall Priſon in the night, and to go forth out of the ſame in the day, under the reſtraint and controll of a continuall Keeper, is alwayes an impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though exerciſed with greater mildneſs and leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And divers cauſes there are to warrant the ſame in <hi>London</hi> rather then in other places: the one is for that the City of <hi>London</hi> ſtandeth chiefely upon the traffique and intercourſe of Merchants, and the uſe of buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their ſundry commodities, which is not alwayes performed by themſelves, but by their factours and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and oftentimes one factour or agent ſerveth the turn of many Merchants, whereby hee is preſſed to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry and ſeverall accounts. Wherefore to the end the priſoners may enform themſelves upon their mutuall reckonings, both what they owe, and what is due unto them, and alſo that upon conference and account with their agents returning from other countreys, they may be made acquainted with the increaſe of their adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or commodities, it is neceſſary they ſhould have places of meeting, which will not be ſo convenient in a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40820:8"/>cloſe priſon, the ſame being no place of aſſembly or free acceſſe (eſpecially it being no common duty in the Gaoler to permit any perſon to come among his priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for any ſuch occaſion) and if the Gaoler were bound to endure and ſuffer ſuch common and voluntary repair unto his priſoners: yet will it be no fit place for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants to treat and negotiate their cauſes, which cannot be well determined without their Books of accounts, and witneſſes of their contracts, and oft muſt the ſame bee decided before the Maſters of their Trades or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. So that this cuſtome made in furtherance of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all accounts,<note place="margin">Vide 4 <hi>E. o.</hi> com. 36.</note> doth very much enable the priſoner to procure his liberty and pay his debt. Alſo if the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be poor and of himſelfe unable to pay, this tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their going abroad with the Keeper, is a good meane for him to procure the Alms, and reliefe of other charitable people, thereby the ſooner to purchaſe his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Whereby it appeareth what reckoning the Law maketh of them, in conſideration of their great hazzard by Sea (through danger of ſhipwrack or piracy) and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in ſtrange Countreys (by falſhood and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Factours) or by wars between Princes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences and miſchiefes whereof, are not ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive or prejudiciall to any, as to Merchants, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as it may by a fortunate voyage be much enriched and advanced: ſo may it by any of the miſchances aforeſaid, be ſo empaired and overthrown, that it may turn himſelfe, his wife, and family to utter calamity and diſtreſſe. Therefore as the hope and comfort of the wife (having commonly no aſſurance of joynture in the City, nor expectation of dower as other women have) and alſo of the children (being for the moſt part born to no great
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40820:8"/>patrimony, other then that which their fathers ſhall by their vertuous induſtry acquire) doth onely depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fortune of their husbands or fathers travaile, it hath laudably and conſcionably been obſerved for a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and is yet by the wiſer and better ſort religiouſly regarded that when any Citizen of <hi>London</hi> dyeth, his wife ſhall have the third part of his goods, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren another third part, equally to be divided among them, according to the proportion of his goods, and himſelfe another third part to diſpoſe by his laſt Will and Teſtament at his pleaſure. A partition ſo reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and grounded upon ſo good conſideration, (the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and eſtate of the <hi>Londoners</hi> conſidered,) that if it were not approved by cuſtome, but to be propoſed in the wiſeſt and higheſt Court of Parliament, whether it were fit to have the force of a Law, I think no man (unleſſe he were a <hi>Timon</hi> by nature, or a <hi>Diogenes</hi> by diſpoſition) no man I ſay poſſeſſed with common humanity would gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay or impugn it. Doth not the common Law now in force give the husband preſently by the intermariage, all the goods and chattells of his wife, though the ſame bee of the value of 10000 pounds, ſo that when ſhee is once his wife, the Law diſableth her to give or diſpoſe any thing that was hers before? And ſhall not the husband be bound by ſemblable Obligation of reaſon to leave his wife the third part of his goods, and if the Law be in that reſpect defective (as what Law in the world, except the Law of God, is without his imperfections?) ſhall not the cuſtome ſupply it in ſuch ſort, that no barbarous and uncharitable or cautelous, and unkinde practiſes by deed of gift, or otherwiſe, ſhall diſappoint or defraud the ſame: eſpecially here in <hi>London,</hi> where the good eſtate of men,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40820:9"/>for the moſt part conſiſteth in movables, by reaſon of their continuall Trades and Exchanges, ſo that their wives cannot aſſure themſelves of their dowry common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called thirds, as they might if their husbands were ſeiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Lands in Fee-ſimple. Alſo the comfortable ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between husband and wife, is of that pretious eſtimate and honourable reputation before God and man, that there may not poſſibly a more ſacred and ſtrait conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be imagined among the children of men. <hi>Charon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> the Philoſopher calleth them <hi>Homoſipios,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, fed with the ſelfe ſame food. And <hi>Epimenides</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Philoſopher calleth them <hi>Homocapnos,</hi> which is as much to ſay, as uſing the ſelfe ſame ſmoke, and the ſelfe ſame manger, and as it were drawing the ſelfe ſame breath. Finally, the Scripture giveth expreſſe charge to each man to tender his wife with extraordinary good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices by ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. ca.</hi> 19. <hi>Mark.</hi> cap. 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> ca. 7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> ca. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt leave thy Father and Mother, and cleave to thy wife.</hi> If the force of cuſtome did not enforce the matter, theſe onely conſiderations were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to prove, that there ſhould be nothing private, nothing peculiar, nothing proper, but every thing in common, every thing equally intereſted between the husband and the wife. The like though not equall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is commanded by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Col.</hi> 3. by the Fathers towards their children. <hi>You fathers be tender and loving unto your children, and diſcourage them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us ſee what account our common Law hath made of the like cuſtomes, founded upon the love and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection between man and wife. It was uſed of ancient time in Gavelkinde Land, and hath received the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and judgement of a good and lawfull cuſtome,<note place="margin">8 <hi>H.M.</hi> 3 Preſ. 60.</note> that if the husband be attainted and executed for a Felony by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40820:9"/>him committed,<note place="margin">8 <hi>E.</hi> 2. It in can. Preſer. 50.</note> yet ſhall his wife for the ſolace of her loſſe and deſolation have her dowry of his Land, and alſo the heire ſhall inherite the ſame according to that old ſaying:<note place="margin">P. 35 <hi>H.</hi> 6.58.</note> 
               <hi>The Father to the Bough, &amp; the Son to the Plough:</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the common law by rigorous imputation to make man more fearfull to offend in crimes of ſuch quality, extendeth the puniſhment though not to the perſons of the wife and children, yet to their fortune ſo farre as it may turn to their utter impoveriſhment and diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>In the City of <hi>York</hi> there is a cuſtome, that the husband may enfeoffe his wife of ſuch Land as he ſhall purchaſe, which though it bee againſt the rule of the common Law (which diſableth the husband to convey any Land to his wife) by feoffement or deed,<note place="margin">12 <hi>H.</hi> 3. Preſ. 6.1.</note> yet by force of the cuſtome it was adjudged to be lawfull and effectuall. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the cuſtome of many places in <hi>England</hi> is, that the wife ſhall enjoy the whole Land of her husband in name of her dowry, as it appeareth by <hi>M. Litt.</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Litt. ti, <hi>Dower.</hi>
               </note> and the husband cannot by any cautele or deviſe defeat her there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And in ſome other Countries they have the moity or tone part, and generally by the common Law the third part. In <hi>Northwales</hi> the cuſtome is ſo beneficiall for wives, (that although they be ſure of their thirds of ſuch Land as their husbands ſhall chance to be ſeiſed of at any time during the mariage) yet are they to have the moity or tone part, not onely of his goods and movea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but alſo of his Leaſes, be the terms thereof never ſo long.<note place="margin">14 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               </note> Not many yeers ago the cuſtome of Taundean was alleaged and allowed by the Court of the Kings Bench, that the husband or wife whether ſo ever of them did happen to over-live ſhould have the inheritance or Fee-ſimple Land of the other by ſurvivor, a cuſtome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40820:10"/>neither contrary to reaſon nor repugnent to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as no well diſpoſed or good husband can deny, when he entreth into conſideration of thoſe holy duties and good obſervances that are commended and commanded in holy Scripture.<note place="margin">Read the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> ca. 5.</note> If then theſe cuſtomes bear ſway in ſundry places, and are publickly approved by judiciall ſentences, what Citizen will be ſo ſenſeleſſe, what <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doner</hi> ſo looſe; what Merchant or other free man ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate; and unregardfull of his own good eſtate, and ſo ready to defile his own neſt, as once to attempt or practiſe the violation or breach of ſo good a cuſtome? What is he who ſeeing the Eſtate of <hi>London</hi> is preferred before other Cities of the Land, by the benefit and means of their moſt profitable cuſtomes, that will give a dangerous example to abrogate the ſame, and to call their uſages in queſtion? A cuſtome, if it have been once notoriouſly diſcontinued, or interrupted, loſeth the title and appellation of a cuſtome, and by inſtance given of the time when it was diſuſed lacketh a great part of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Then unnaturall or at leaſt wiſe unadviſed is that Citizen which to ſerve his private humour bringeth a generall cuſtome either into queſtion by his fraud,<note place="margin">See before in the caſe of Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, how carefull the City was to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void this danger and to preſerve their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and and in the caſe of the attaint be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 7 <hi>H.</hi> 6, &amp;c.</note> or by his example into contempt. Pernicious alſo is the preſident of one cuſtome called in queſtion to the ruine of the reſt: Namely; when as the City by their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell in her Majeſties Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> claiming the benefit of their cuſtomes, may be encountred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted, with a counter plea given by themſelves, that ſuch of their own Aldermen and commons have by their deeds and deviſes either diſaffirmed or diſanulled the ſame. A practiſe as of great condemnation in them that do it, ſo no doubt of great overſight and incircumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them that ſuffer it.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:40820:10"/>
            <p>But ſomewhat to ſatisfie the idle cavils pretended to the contrary, ſaith ſome one, is not the generall Law of <hi>England</hi> ſufficient to manage the government of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> as well as of all other Subjects, but that <hi>Londoners</hi> muſt have private cuſtomes and uſages of their own? This objection made by the enviers or enemies of the wealth of <hi>London</hi> (howſoever they make ſhew to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) rather deſerveth a hiſſe then a reply, and is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently confuted in the former diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But it is further urged by ſome hard husbands, My wife is froward and undutifull, and hath not deſerved it. Shee is a fool and cannot rule it. She will marry again, and enrich ſome other with the fruit of my travaile. Wherefore I think it neceſſary to abridge her of that liberality which the cuſtome doth extend. Alſo my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be evill enclined, diſobedient or untractable, or ſome of them be. Wherefore I may with reaſon deprive them of the benefit of this cuſtome. Firſt to anſwer the undutifulneſs, I wiſh thee whoſoever thou art to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and convent thy ſelfe to the tribunall ſeat of thy inward minde, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> in lib. confeſſ.</note> and to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thy Judge, thy cogitations the Witneſſes, thy actions the accuſers, thy memory the regiſter or record to give in evidence: and let it be diſcuſſed in all due cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, whether thou didſt not likewiſe forget the offices of a good husband and defraud her of her duties, (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) or provoke her to impatience which the ſame Apoſtle forbiddeth in theſe words,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> ca. 7. <hi>Col.</hi> ca. 3.</note> 
               <hi>You husbands be loving to your wives, and no way be bitter unto them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 1. ca. 1.</note> Which alſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> remembreth in adviſing husbands to dwell with their wives ſincerely and according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in doing honour unto them as to the weaker Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40820:11"/>Let it I ſay be examined in the conſiſtory of thy conſcience whether thou either by thy fault wittingly, or negligently by thy default, or by thy unkindneſs undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, haſt cauſed her being the weaker veſſell to bee the more intolerable. If thou find thy ſelfe condemned by thy conſcience, let remorſe be thy executioner, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment with kindneſs towards thy wife be thy pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: but if thou finde thy ſelfe guilty of no want of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, love or good carriage of thy ſelfe towards her, ſo that her undutifulneſs proceeded of her ſelfe: yet I pray thee remember the benefits which God hath given thee by her means, whether they be gifts of fortune in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of thy eſtate, or eſchewing of ſin, by her lawfull and comfortable company, or the bleſſing of children, a ſoveraign good in this world, thy children being the monuments of thy life and being upon earth, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payrers of thy decay. And let theſe favours and graces enjoyed by her company cover and countervaile her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imperfections whatſoever. Follow therein the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the wiſe <hi>Socrates,</hi> who being demanded how he could endure the continuall ſcolding and vexation of his wife <hi>Xantippe,</hi> likewiſe asked of the other why he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cackling and unpleaſant noiſe of Hens and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes in his houſe, Becauſe ſaid the other they lay Egges and breed Chickens for me: and ſo ſaid <hi>Socrates Xantippe</hi> beareth me Children, which good turn alone covereth and diſpenſeth with infinite defects. <hi>Callicratides</hi> the Athenian being demanded why hee a man ſo nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, but having matched with a baſe <hi>Theſſalian</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet by his laſt Will bequeathed unto her all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, leaving his other friends and kinsfolkes unregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: becauſe (ſaid he) ſhe is my wife, meaning that ſhee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40820:11"/>who was by his judgement and choice made worthy to be his wife, ſhould bee unworthy of nothing that was his. Which may alſo ſatisfie that ſecond point of ſuppoſed folly in the wife, &amp; want of diſcretion to marſhal ſo great a proportion of wealth, as the cuſtome will give her. Wherefore wouldeſt thou mary with a fool, if thou thoughteſt her unworthy of the rights of mariage? then ſeeing thy choice hath eſtopped thy Teſtimony of her folly, thy duty towards thy wife ſhall binde thee to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and conceale her weakeneſs, and to perform that which the cuſtome pronounceth to be convenient. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be evill beſtowed upon her, whoſe right by cuſtome demandeth it, and whoſe eſtate and imperfections have need of it, whereas if the husband may be permitted by this colour to defeat his wife, many inconveniences and diſorders might enſue.</p>
            <p>Firſt a generall cuſtome,<note place="margin">Leges ſe accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ad ea quae fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentius non quae raro acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. <hi>Bartolus.</hi>
               </note> which is as alſo a generall Law, never provided for ſuch rare accidents as ſeldome fall in experience, but for things that ordinarily and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happen, ſhould be broken, to the generall ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale and offenſive example of all through the inhability of one, which were a thing unreaſonable. Likewiſe then might husbands, (if that were admitted for a juſt allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) eaſily deviſe and publiſh that or ſome other imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to be in their wives, and thereby bereave them of their right. No more then it is a juſt counterplea or barre to a womans dower to alleage that ſhe is a fool, no more is the imputation of ſuch ſimplicity honeſt and ſufficient to exclude her from her Portion. No it is well ſaid and maintained for a <hi>Maxime</hi> in the Common Law, <hi>Better it is to ſuffer a miſchiefe then an inconvenience.</hi> Leſſe harmfull and hatefull it is for a man to ſwallow
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40820:12"/>twenty of theſe light offences, and to digeſt ſundry of theſe pretenſed ſcruples, then by violating of a cuſtome no leſſe common then commendable to leave to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty an odious memory and obloquie of his name.</p>
            <p>The laſt objection againſt wives is no leſſe ridiculous then Tyrannicall, grounded upon an unjuſt deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from mariage. Mariage is an honourable Ordinance of God, fit and neceſſary for all perſons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed thereunto, to the avoiding of ſinne, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a comfortable and ſociable Chriſtian life. To reſtrain or prohibit the ſame either in maides or widows, (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) is the doctrine of divells.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> ep. 1. ca. 4. 43 <hi>E.</hi> 3.6.</note> And to indent or condition with any that he or ſhe ſhall not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is a condition limited againſt Law, and by the ſame pronounced unlawfull and unreaſonable. Make it thine own caſe, admit thou dideſt match with a wealthy wife, whoſe furniture and riches hath increaſed thy Eſtate, if God ſhould call for her, wouldeſt thou in a kinde memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the benefits attained by her meanes, make thy ſelfe a votary to live unmaried? Do thoſe which mary great Heires being women, and after their wives deaths enjoy their whole inheritance by the curteſie of <hi>England,</hi> making their wives heires to expect during their lives, take it for any matter of conſcience or ſcruple to mary again? Unleſſe it be in ſome place where the force of the cuſtome and the benefit of the living joyned together work a contrary reſolution in ſome husbands: which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome annexed to <hi>Gavelkinde</hi> Lands in <hi>Kent</hi> and other places is of this quality,<note place="margin">16 <hi>E.</hi> 3. aid 129. 19 <hi>E.</hi> 3. aid 144.</note> that the husband ſhall after the deceaſe of his wife be Tenant by the curteſie of her land as long as he remaineth unmaried, whether he have iſſue by her or not: but upon his next mariage ſhall utterly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40820:12"/>forgo all his intereſt therein. A cuſtome therefore the leſſe unreaſonable becauſe the reſtraint of mariage of the one ſide is countervailed by the beneficiall favour of the other ſide to have the land by the curteſie without iſſue, and alſo for that hee is to deprive the next Heire of his wife, who perchance hath been maried with him but few moneths or dayes, of the profit and commodity of the whole Land during his life. But chiefely becauſe it is a cuſtom grounded and grown in continuance to ſuch reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious obſervation and regard, that it ſeemeth an offence of conſcience to infringe it. But in our caſe ſithence there is neither cuſtome nor conſcience to warrant thy will, why ſhouldeſt thou then ſeem to quarrell with the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liberty of thy wife, if ſhe ſurvive thee, ſhe being weak by kinde and education, and thereby leſſe able to direct her occaſions, and govern her eſtate without a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and coadjutor? no, on Gods name referre her to her own choice and conſcience therein, and make it no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe and colour to abridge her of her right, becauſe ſhee ſeemeth inclinable unto that, which God hath ordained, and all men and women do embrace. As to the fear and ſuſpicion pretended, that another in matching with thy wife ſhould be enriched by thy travaile, what ſhould move thee to make that ſuperſtitious account of thy goods when thou art gone? Were they any longer thine, then while thou hadſt life and licence to employ them? Thou muſt needs know and acknowledge beſides thy daily experience, by the very Etymologie and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, the true nature and quality of the thing. Theſe worldly goods are called temporall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſerve one but for a time; they are termed tranſitory, for that their property is fleeting from one
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40820:13"/>owner unto an other; they are named moveable or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, becauſe all their grace and credite is in running and removing into divers hands, according to that rude and old (but yet true) Latine rime.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Omnia mundana per vices ſunt aliena,</l>
               <l>Nunc mea, nunc hujus, poſt mortem ſunt alterius.</l>
               <l>This worldly wealth each day doth change</l>
               <l>Their owners as we ſee,</l>
               <l>Now mine, now his, and after death</l>
               <l>An others goods they be.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Then ſithence thy wealth hath waited upon thee all thy life long, wouldeſt thou require the ſame to reſt at thy devotion after thy death? If that ſeem impertinent and unprofitable unto thee, then relinquiſh this care and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the goods of this world to have their naturall courſe and condition, which is to be ſtill in exchange, paſſage, and poſting from hand to hand, ſerving all men, <hi>ut pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinationis viaticum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> That is, <hi>A Pilgrims charge or defray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his journey,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hicrome</hi> termeth it. And addreſs thy minde to the deſire of ſuch goods as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their temporal, tranſitory, current nor moveable, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, permanent, conſtant, and not onely immutable but ineſtimable.</p>
            <p>But finally to ſatisfie the laſt objection againſt thy children, I wiſh thee to look back unto that I have ſaid, that thou mayeſt not for a private injury or diſpleaſure, ſeem as much as lyeth in thee to ſupplant and abrogate a publick cuſtome, to the no leſſe prejudice then offence of a great number that have intereſt therein. In enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy Son, thou doſt diſcharge the duty of a naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards him, which if hee prodigally or wickedly miſpend or abuſe, he carryeth his own condemnation and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40820:13"/>proveth a wilfull enemy to himſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25.</note> The good father mentioned in the Goſpell, who at the ſuite of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull and diſobedient Son, (that would needs abandon the ſervice and attendance on his father to run the courſe of an extravagant Libertine with lewd company) gave him a great portion of his wealth, is not any way blamed by our Saviour for that indulgence, but rather recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to all poſterity as a true Pattern of a kind father. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth the father to be well affected to his children, and no way to diſcourage them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> c. 3.</note> What may breed greater diſcouragement or diſcontentment in any childe, then to ſee himſelfe by the place of his birth, and the good fortune of the City intitled to the commodity of a good cuſtome, and yet injuriouſly by his own father, (whoſe affection ſhould be alwayes occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied and earneſt in procuring the good of his children) diſappointed of his hope &amp; defrauded of his right. And as well as ſome having juſt cauſe of diſpleaſure againſt their Sonne and childe, may in this unlawfull and diſorderly ſort practiſe their revenge, ſo may ſome other inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and wilfull father upon a conceipt taken againſt a good Sonne and of ſingular deſert, for that he concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not with him in ſome humour or diſpoſition, moſt wrongfully diſtreſſe and undo him by ſuch a preſident. Thus the miſchiefes objected on the one ſide are light and of ſmall moment, whereas the inconveniences ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent on the other ſide be manifold and of dangerous conſequence.</p>
            <p>I will not vouchſafe to anſwer that undiſcreet <hi>Sarcaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> or bitter ſcoffe that ſome uſe, <hi>We may play our wealth at dice without offence to the cuſtome, wherefore ſhould wee not then diſpoſe the ſame from our wife and children</hi> by our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40820:14"/>deeds of gift? This amounteth to as much as if a maried man would ſay, I may commit felony or treaſon, and be attainted and hanged therefore, and then the Law giveth my wife no dower, nor my heire no patrimony, then why ſhould I not in reaſon uſe my diſcretion with the Land without incumbrance by the one, or injury to the other? Match theſe two caſes together with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thou ſhalt perceive they have a ſenſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currency in their addreſs and application to this purpoſe. It is well ſaid by the Poet.</p>
            <q>il juvat exemplum quod litem lite reſolvit.</q>
            <p>The example of one wilfull or wicked act giveth no juſt countenance or allowance to another. Let ſo much ſaid to thy objections take ſome place to alter thine hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or at leaſt be a preparative for thine own reaſon in the fear of God to purge thee of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this ſhort diſcourſe with one conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of great importance, I wiſh thee to conſider, that this City of <hi>London</hi> is and hath been happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in this flouriſhing proſperity by the wiſe and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick conſent that all and alwayes the particulars have had to increaſe the generall good eſtate thereof, thinking it their duty as they got and acquired their ſubſtance in this City, ſo alſo to ſpend and defray it in the ſame: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that whatſoever falleth from the one commeth and groweth unto another, and by alteration of private fortunes (as chances and changes of times doe require from one Citizen to another) the generall eſtate hath flouriſhed, and never wanted particular men of wealth and ability to ſuſtain the offices and functions of the City. Upon which conſideration by moſt laudable and antient Cuſtome, the Lord Maior and Senate of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40820:14"/>have been and are intitled to the tuition and cuſtody of young <hi>Orphans</hi> and their goods, and likewiſe are made acquainted by ordinary good means of inventaries taken and produced, what ſubſtance and wealth each man dyeth poſſeſſed of, to the intent that although that man which by his good travaile and Trade hath grown to be rich among them, be departed hence, yet his goods may remain as among his wife and children in uſe and property, ſo to the generall ſtrength of this City in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and reckoning. For wee often ſee that one rich mans wealth paſſeth to the increaſe of the good eſtate of another Citizen, either by mariage of the widow, or of the Orphan: ſo that the City though deprived of a member or inhabitant, yet is not deſtitute of ſuch as may diſcharge his employment and place. Whereas if this pernicious practiſe and uncharitable liberty might take root by deeds of gifts and cautelous conveyance to ſtrangers, not onely the wife and children may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, but alſo the ſtate of the City much weakened, and in danger of a great diſreputation and decay, from that that it hath bin and yet is. For if it be adjudged law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in one, of what degree ſoever he be, it is neither im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible nor unlikely, that the ſame will be uſed by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and conſequently may be practiſed by all: which if it befall, what will become of the happy condition of this City, it is not hard to conjecture. I mean not to extend my ſpeech to the prejudice of any true debts that a man oweth without fraud or colluſion, ſeeing the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome very providently careth for the diſcharge thereof, but my purpoſe is to diſſwade men from evill example, from inſolent violation of good cuſtomes, and from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and unſeemly practiſes of deceit and evill meaning
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40820:15"/>towards their wives and children: Which perſwaſion I would wiſh all profeſſors of the Law ſeriouſly and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to uſe and enforce to their clients, being Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> as in good conſcience and diſcretion they ought to do.</p>
            <p>Blame not my bold enterpriſe (gentle Reader) nor reprove my ſimple cenſure herein preſented unto thee,<note place="margin">An Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe to the Reader, and the motive of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> which might I know both for the matter &amp; manner of it have been by any other, and perchance by my ſelfe more largely and effectually delivered: if the opportunity of my leaſure might have anſwered the quality of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I had in hand. But fearing leſt I ſhould with too long a diſcourſe in ſo plain a propoſition breed more lothſomneſs then liking, I would not, for want of leaſure I might not, and if I had had time at will I mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not (ſeeing for any urgent occaſion, the error being yet freſh, the practiſe rare and not grown to an enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I needed not) but in a word or two to make thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the cauſe that moved me to addreſſe theſe few reaſons to thy gentle view, So it happened, that I being in company and conference with ſome perſons (though otherwiſe wiſe &amp; wel-affected, yet in this matter ſtrangely conceited) it chanced that the lawfulneſſe and conveniency of this cuſtome came in queſtion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate among us, and was by ſome of them (being men for ſufficiency, of great opinion, and for countenance and credite of good apparance and regard in the City) ſo preſſed with objections, that the moſt part of thoſe which were preſent ſeemed to encline to that perſwaſion. Wherefore leſt the authority of the men might the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſeduce the ſimple multitude unto their error, and for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40820:15"/>that I thought it a charitable policy to prevent the perill in the prime, before it grew to a feſtering ſore or incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evill, according to the Poet <hi>Ovids</hi> adviſe,
<q>
                  <l>Principiis obſta: ſero medicina paratur,</l>
                  <l>Cum mala per longas invaluere moras.</l>
                  <l>VVithſtand at firſt the ſpringing evill</l>
                  <l>VVith medicines fit therefore,</l>
                  <l>Too late it is to take the cure</l>
                  <l>Of old and feſtred ſore.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I thought good to apply this ſimple Receipt of reaſon to the minds of all ſuch as ſhall chance to be diſtempered be theſe diſſwaſions: hoping that they will yeeld me that friendly requitall of good conſtruction, which my offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red good will may ſeem to deſerve: and although I keep my ſelfe unnamed, and unknown, it may pleaſe them to have this opinion of me, no more favourable then reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that he which is well devoted to the defence of good cuſtomes, is rather to be juſtified in his good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then condemned or held ſuſpected of any ſiniſter conceipt.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents_of_missing_part">
            <pb facs="tcp:40820:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>GOvernours Charge.</item>
               <item>Preſident. <hi>Fol. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Treaſurer. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Surveyors. <hi>Fol. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Almoners. <hi>Fol. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scrutiners. <hi>Fol. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Admonition to the Auditors. <hi>Fol. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Orders for keeping the Evidences. <hi>Fol. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Renter Clerk and his Charge. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hoſpitalers Office. <hi>Fol. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Stewards Office. <hi>Fol. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Matrons Office. <hi>Fol. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Siſters Office. <hi>Fol. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Chirurgians. <hi>Fol. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Porter. <hi>Fol. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Bedells. <hi>Fol. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Viſitor of <hi>Newgate. Fol. 27</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40820:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
